From Gustav II Adolf becoming king until Karl XII is shot and dies.
What happened during the Great Power time?
Why was 60 % of the kings Karl?
And how was the life of ordinary people in Sweden when the country was greatest?
What we see here are the remains of three 16th century shirts.
What makes them special is all stains, and there are blood stains.
These are the three shirts like Gustav II Adolf Bar-
-When he found dead on the battlefield at Lützen.
Sweden's first 17th century king dies in today's Germany, 37 years old.
He is called the lion of the Nordic countries, and Sweden appears as a great power.
How is that possible?
How has the sparsely populated, neglected country in northern Europe ended up here?
Some we can probably thank Gustav II Adolf's grandfather Gustav for.
It comes from the 16th century.
Gustav Vasa has united the country.
He has built up a military power and an administration - a modern state.
Sweden does not look like today.
The kingdom is smaller in the south and west, but Finland is included.
Stockholm is centrally located in the country where transport is mostly done at sea.
Sweden has developed into a more modern and cohesive kingdom.
Developments are not just happening in Sweden.
Around Europe throughout Europe, the princes build up strong nations.
In the 17th century they stand there with their strong armies and fleets-
-And is ready to put them into work.
And then we get these big wars.
Here is Gustav II Adolf in better condition than on the battlefield down in Lützen.
Not a single blood stain on the collar.
In the fall of 1611 he takes over the throne of his hard-by-father father Karl Ix-
-With a war -tired population at home and a lot of soldiers in Germany.
This will be a crisis in Sweden that you still do quite well.
Chancellor Axel Oxenstierna gets a strong role-
-And you decide to stay in the war.
Kristina will take over the throne and study everything a regent needs to know.
She is seen as brilliant and brilliant-
-But is she more brilliant than anyone else?
In any case, she is interested in these issues.
Through the wars down in Europe, it brings in books and knowledge-
-As comes from the conquered areas.
This pompous mantle carries Kristina when she is crowned to Swedish queen.
Before the National Council, she says that she never intends to marry anyone.
But it will be even more shocking, because in June 1654 the Queen tells you
-That she has decided to abdicate.
It will soon come out that she will convert and become Catholic.
The religion that the father has fought for and made himself known for-
-The she abanders it and joins the same team as his main enemies.
And she allies with the Pope in Rome.
It is unspeakably large.
More were probably rendered in Sweden, but not everyone could move to Italy.
It is miserable, plague and so cold that it is called the small ice age.
What did the Swedes do for fun?
During the Great Power, people played a lot-
-And is happy to make a party.
There were not many days in the calendar without any festive event.
Then all who had worked in the village- gathered
-and there was beer, dance, music, games and food.
Young people wanted to meet, and they were a little neighbor an engine in the party.
Often the young people were left at last
-And the priest and others were horrified at their playing and dancing.
Now people also imagine that some can be something other than people.
Witches.
The witch processes are a defined period called the great noise.
Sometimes you get the image that the witch processes took place throughout the country.
That's not really true.
Under the great noise, as it is called many screaming in the phas-
-for what they were exposed to
-About three hundred women and the occasional magician are executed.
Life is better for the half -percent of the population that controls - the nobility.
They live in abundance thanks to the wars-
-And many stately castles and houses are being built around Sweden.
But despite beautiful dwellings and comfortable beds, the women are not so free.
They first belong to their father and then their husband.
He has realized that the achievements of his father have reached-
-Where somewhere is probably Sweden's capacity.
He reigns Sweden during peacetime and has time to organize the country.
He changes the military selection and regains properties from nobility-
-In the so -called reduction.
He dies 41 years old in stomach cancer as a very popular and popular king.
His teenage son takes over the kingdom.
When the country has a young, inexperienced king, Sweden's enemies attack at the same time.
Now comes the Great Nordic War - all against Sweden.
Karl XII is 18 years old, and the enemies believe he should not be so experienced
-Or manage to handle this collected onslaught of three enemies.
Denmark gives up as soon as he lands there.
He defeats the Russian army in Narva and wins even at Riga.
Rumor has begun to go that the Swedish king is invincible.
Then they reach Poltava, and there is not as good at all.
Karl XII loses the battle at Poltava.
Suddenly, Karl XII has no field army and is close to being captured.
He simply has to escape with what remains of his troops.
He flees to Turkey and remains for 5 years.
Meanwhile, the plague reaches Sweden.
One third of Stockholm's population dies.
In the kingdom over 100,000 people.
When the king returns, the country is super poor and badly infected.
Russia has knocked the Baltic.
A war becomes the end of Karl XII's life.
In 1718 in a trenches in the Norwegian city of Fredrikshald-
-He is met by a bullet in his head.
He has never had time to get a son-
-On all life struggled to keep the great kingdom he has inherited.
I've always seen it as some kind of very sad, but true, vignette-
-To the end for the time of the superpower.
This is how many have a picture of the equality - from a known painting.
The picture has been seen by generations and everyone thinks that this is how it went.
It didn't.
Did he lie on a stretcher?
No, he lay in a pine box.
A coffin, simply.
Was he carried over the mountain ranges?
The dramatic mountains.
Not at all.
He was shot in southern Norway.
There are soft ridges, rolling hills.
But why do you portray Karl XII's equality in this way?
Well, to create a sense of the nation Sweden.
We want a common history.
Common heroes are good and Karl XII is becoming a hero.
He becomes Swedish.
The great power period has for a long time been told with a romantic shimmer-
-There brave heroes won a blow after blows.
But war is also dead and suffering, both for the losers and for the winners.
What are the traces after the time of the Great Power?
Sweden is a moral superpower that tells the world what to do.
Geographically, the tracks are clear.
Skåne, Blekinge, Bohuslän and Halland have been Swedish ever since.
And although it was mostly war, both Gustav II Adolf and Karl XI-
-Inat and change things in Sweden's administration that still remain today.
Most of us, if we were to go back in time and live that life-
-Would probably think it was difficult.
Swedish Setting: Elin Dahlqvist Iyuno-Di Group for UR